A Guide to the Jean D. Hellmuth Papers, 1976-1992
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Jean D. Hellmuth Papers, 1976-1992
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 304
3 Linear feet
Jean D. Hellmuth
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was a gift to Special Collections & Archives from Jean D. Hellmuth in April 1995. A second deposit of materials was made in 1996.
Biographical/Historical Information
Jean D. Hellmuth was actively involved in the attempt to ratify the Equal Rights Amendment in Virginia as well as many other women's issues.
Scope and Content Information
The collection includes minutes, correspondence, reports, newsletters, newspaper clippings, various publications and other materials related to the attempt to ratify the Equal Rights Amendment in Virginia and other women's issues. The materials date from the late 1970s until the early 1990s. A significant portion of the collection is comprised of materials of the Virginia ERA Ratification Council.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Materials arranged alphabetically and chronologically therein.
Organization
The collection has been arranged into two separate series. Series I is made up of material collected by Hellmuth, most of which is related to the effort to ratify the Equal Suffrage Amendment in Virginia.
Series II is comprised of the correspondence, minutes and other materials of the Virginia ERA Ratification Council.
Contents List
- Personal
  - Calendar 1980, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Critical Comments on A Lesser Life, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Ephemera (Box 1)
  - Ephemera-Bumper Stickers (Box 1)
  - Ephemera-Flyers and Pamphlets (1 of 3) (Box 1)
  - Ephemera-Flyers and pamphlets (2 of 3) (Box 1)
  - Ephemera-Flyers and Pamphlets (3 of 3) (Box 1)
  - ERA January-February 1985 (Box 1)
  - ERA Extension 1978 (Box 2)
  - ERA Materials 1987-1990 (Box 2)
  - ERA Response Letters (General Assembly) (Box 2)
  - National Woman's Party (Box 2)
  - Publications (Box 2)
  - Status of Women in the U.S. 1986 (Box 2)
  - Virginia Women's Meeting June 1977 (Box 2)
  - Woman Activist Fund Advisory Committee 1988 (Box 2)
- Virginia ERA Ratification Council
  - Activities 1981 (Box 2)
  - Ad Signers (prospective) (Box 2)
  - Advertisements (Box 2)
  - Agendas (current) (Box 2)
  - Art Show, n.d., 1978 (Box 2)
  - Attorney General 1976-1978 (Box 2)
  - Brethren, The-Woodward and Armstrong (Box 2)
  - Bulletin Board Materials (Muriel Smith's ERA office) 1979 (Box 2)
  - Chronology (Box 2)
  - Clippings 1978-1982 (Box 2)
  - Common Cause (Box 2)
  - Convention for Women 1981 (Box 2)
  - Congressional Caucus for Women's Issues, Equal Rights Briefing (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1971-1982 (Box 3)
  - Ephemera, including ERA bumper sticker (Box 3)
  - The Equal Rights Amendment Handbook (Box 3)
  - ERA Debate, March 1979 (Box 3)
  - ERA Publications (Box 3)
  - ERA Vigils 1980s (Box 3)
  - ERA Vigils 1990s (Box 3)
  - Forms (Box 3)
  - Issues (Box 3)
  - Labor Employment (Box 3)
  - Legislative History/Analysis, n.d., 1980s-1990s (Box 3)
  - Lobbying Guides/Aides (Box 3)
  - Membership file (?) (Box 4)
  - Military (Box 4)
  - Minutes 1978-1986 (Box 4)
  - Minutes, Correspondence, Notes 1986 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous-Correspondence, Publications, Notes (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous-Correspondence, Notes n.d., 1970s-1980s (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous-minutes, notes, correspondence (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Publications (mostly ERA related) (Box 5)
  - National Women's Conference Committee (NWCC) (Box 6)
  - Notebook (Box 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, n.d., 1970s-1990s (Box 6)
  - Petitions for ERA (Box 6)
  - Political Activity 1976, 1978 (Box 6)
  - Political Campaigns 1979 (Box 6)
  - Pro-ERA Conferences, Public Meetings 1976-1981 (Box 6)
  - Projects 1976-1977 (Box 6)
  - Project/Ideas (Box 6)
  - VERARC Publications 1974-1989 (Box 6)
  - Reference Materials (Box 6)
  - Referendum Project 1977, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Refusals to Donate 1982 (Box 7)
  - Religious Support (Box 7)
  - Richmond Human Rights Coalition (Box 7)
  - Richmond Women's Caucus for Art 1984-1985 (Box 7)
  - Sexual Harassment/Assault, n.d., 1979-1980 (Box 7)
  - Socialist Workers Party 1977 (Box 7)
  - State Fair 1981 (Box 7)
  - Statements and Comments 1976-1981 (Box 7)
  - Strategy 1976, 1979-1980 (Box 7)
  - Television (Box 7)
  - Theater/Bash (Box 7)
  - Update-Congressional Caucus for Women's Issues 1985 (Box 7)
  - Vigil Book 1979-1980 (Box 7)
  - Virginia Council on Social Welfare (Box 7)
  - Virginia ERA Legislator's Kit (Box 7)
  - Virginia Equal Rights Amendment Ratification Council (VERARC) (Box 7)
  - Virginia General Assembly Voting Record 1979 (Box 7)
  - Virginia Ratification Project (Box 7)
  - Volunteers: NOW, n.d., 1981 (Box 7)
  - White House Briefing 1977 (Box 7)
  - Woman Activist, The 1984-1992 (Box 7)
  - Women in Government (Box 7)
  - Women's Action Alliance (Box 7)
  - Women of Virginia, Rights You Are Denied 1983 (Box 7)
  - Photographs--ERA Vigil (5), n.d. (Box 8)
  - Political Campaign Buttons (Box 8)
  - Political Campaign Buttons-Vote Democratic (3) (Box 8)
  - Political Campaign Buttons-I Believe in Henry Howell (2) (Box 8)
  - Slides-State Fair (3) 1981 (Box 8)
  - The Equal Rights Amendment and YOU Posters (Oversize 25)
  - Credit for Women, Your Rights Under the Equal Credit Opportunity Act, Poster (Oversize 25)